<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in a country-audience on the late day of fasting and prayer, January 30 by a priest of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Cave, John, d. 1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31405</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36288</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15632864</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15632864</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31405)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1183:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in a country-audience on the late day of fasting and prayer, January 30 by a priest of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Cave, John, d. 1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Cave by Wing.</note>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, Feb. 20. 1678/9. Guil. Sill."--T.p. verso.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, II, 1-2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104261:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in a Country-Audience On the late Day of <hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> JANUARY 30. By a Prieſt of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Orig. contra Celſum lib. <hi>8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The eyes of the Lord are upon the righteous, and his ears are open unto their cry.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 34.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:104261:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R,</p>
            <closer>
               <date>Feb. <hi>20. 1678/9.</hi>
               </date>
               <signed>Guil. Sill.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104261:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached in a Country-Audience On the late Day of <hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> JANUARY 30.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 TIM. li. 1, 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I exhort therefore that firſt of all Supplications, Prayers, Interceſſions and giving of thanks be made for all men:</p>
                  <p>For Kings and all that are in authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Know no time more ſeaſonable to recommend to you this great and general Duty of Prayer, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for our ſelves and others, Prayer for the whole body of the Nation, <hi>prayer for all men,</hi> than up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this day of Solemn publick Faſting and Prayer.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104261:3"/>
            <p>I know no time more ſeaſonable to recommend to you the eſpecial duty of Prayer for Kings and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, than upon this day which gives us ſo ſorrowful a remembrance of the fatal fall of the beſt of Princes, and therein too evident a proof of the great dangers that even ſuch are expoſed to, and conſequently of the great need they ſtand in of our Prayers. And I know no words more proper to mind you of the duty of Prayer in general, or of this particular duty of Praying for Kings and Governours, than theſe of our Apoſtle: which contain a fatherly admonition of <hi>Paul,</hi> the aged, to his Son <hi>Timothy,</hi> That in the overſight of his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs he would take ſpecial care that ſolemn-Prayers be duly put up to Almighty God in the ſeveral aſſemblies of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>For all Men,</hi> not only for Believers, but for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels; not only for Friends and Relations, but for Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Perſecutors.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For Men of Place and power, <hi>for Kings and all that are in authority.</hi> After which,</p>
            <p n="3">3. He propounds a motive to procure Prayers for ſuch eſpecially, <hi>viz. that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty;</hi> That ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and righteouſneſs may be ſo encouraged and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by the religious care and zeal <hi>of thoſe that are in authority,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 32.17.</note> 
               <hi>that we may enjoy the fruit of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which is peace, and the effect of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which is quietneſs and aſſurance for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I exhort therefore, that firſt of all, ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions and giving of thanks be made for all men: For Kings and all that are in authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and honeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe ſeveral words, <hi>Supplications, Prayers, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104261:3"/>are generally underſtood to ſignify ſeveral ſorts of Prayer; The firſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>deprecations</hi> of evil, whether of ſin, or puniſhment. The ſecond <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>petitions</hi> for all thoſe good things which reſpect either this preſent life, or that which is to come. The third <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Interceſſions or Praying for other Men. To be ſure under them with that other of <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> our Apoſtle comprehends all kinds of Prayer, which he would have uſed in its proper place, for its proper ends and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>We need not diſtinguiſh nicely of the different ſenſe of each word, becauſe the Apoſtle might well uſe three words of the ſame, or very near the ſame ſignification, the more throughly to commend to us, and the more earneſtly to preſs upon us, the neceſſity and benefit of devout, fervent, and conſtant <hi>Prayer: I exhort there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions be made,</hi> and I exhort it before all other things as the principal duty of Religion, which is to take place of all the reſt. <hi>I exhort to it firſt of all, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In my diſcourſe upon this ſubject I ſhall ſpeak,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the duty of Praying for all Men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of our particular obligation to pray for Kings, and Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall make uſe of the motive in the Text, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome others, to enforce this expreſſion of our Loyalty, by praying for the King and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a Chriſtian duty to Pray for all Men, for all ſorts and conditions of Men; for Heathen and Jewiſh Infidels, as well as for believing Chriſtians; for all, that err and are ſeduced, as well as for thoſe that are ſound in the Faith; for our enemies and perſecutors as well as for our friends and relations; We are to pray for the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104261:4"/>converſion of the one, as well as the confirmation of the other; for reconcilement to our Enemies, as well as for the continuance of amity with our Friends.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> upon this place laments not only the narrowneſs, and contraction, of this charitable devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but alſo the total defect of it in many Men, and the contrary vice in ſome: Some upon all occaſions pray againſt, and curſe their Neighbours, wiſhing evil may befal them; others think they do very well, if they pray for their friends and acquaintance, for thoſe that have done them good,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or are like to do ſo. The firſt ſort pray like Heathens, the ſecond but like Jews at beſt. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Let us learn to pray like Chriſtians, not only forgiving our enemies, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching God to forgive them too; That we may ſay with the Apoſtles, <hi>Being reviled we bleſs, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted we ſuffer it, being deſamed we intreat,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.12.</note> We endeavour to pacify them by mild and ſoft anſwers, ſay ſome Interpreters; we pray to God for them, we beg that he would pardon them, and turn their hearts, ſay others. The good Chriſtian practiſeth both: <hi>He is gentle towards all men, and prays for thoſe who deſpightfully uſe him and perſecute him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Glory and excellency of the <hi>Chriſtian Spirit,</hi> by this it bore up and maintained its reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and renown, when the world was moſt bent to blaſt and deſtroy it; By this it got ground of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philoſophy, made its way through all the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Arms, and Arts, and took poſſeſſion of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> the moſt powerful and the moſt learned parts of the world. For nothing ever gained a greater eſteem, or procured better entertainment for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of our Saviour, than the patient ſufferings of its primitive profeſſors, and their unparalleled kindneſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104261:4"/>to their moſt malicious and bloody Perſecutors; and it hath been obſerved throughout all ages, that <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> have been the Churches moſt ſerviceable weapons.</p>
            <p>Great profeſſors of Religion, 'tis true, have conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by other Arms; but theſe alone make Religion it ſelf victorious; Theſe keep the Crown upon its head, maintain its Royalties, uphold its Honour and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the World; Theſe <hi>ſet Chriſt upon his throne indeed,</hi> and eſtabliſh his Kingdom in the hearts of Men. And what did ever more ſhake and weaken the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Religion, than the zealous endeavours of high pretenders to promote it by violence and force of Arms? When inſtead of <hi>Exhortations</hi> to <hi>Supplication, Prayer and Interceſſion,</hi> We have heard of nothing, but <hi>curſe ye Meroz, and to your tents O Iſrael:</hi> nothing but encouragement to Mutiny, inſtigations to Sedition, and beatings up for Rebellion, and all this under the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Religion, and a goodly talk of Reformation; but how much this tended to the ſcandal and real damage of Religion, to the planting and watering of Infidelity and Atheiſm, we ought this day eſpecially to conſider and bewail: And in our ſad review of the calamities of the late Civil War, nothing ought to afflict us more, than the impairing of the credit of Religion thereby; though thanks be to God there is no juſt reaſon that this ſhould in the leaſt touch or blemiſh the Honour of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> for we know now too well whence the Doctrines come of Rebelling againſt, of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and murdering of Kings; we know the Plot of this days bloody Tragedy was laid at <hi>Rome,</hi> and acted by the Sects of their making among our ſelves.</p>
            <p>As in the murder of King <hi>Joaſh,</hi> of which we read, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.26. we are given to underſtand that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104261:5"/>none of the Profeſſors of the true Religion had any hand in it; None of the Iſraelites, but <hi>Zabad</hi> the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monite,</hi> and <hi>Jehozabad</hi> the <hi>Moabite:</hi> So we may ſay of the crying wickedneſs of this day, No true <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> had any thing to do in it, none but <hi>the Agents and Emiſſaries of Rome;</hi> none but a faction influenced by <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> principles. But this by the way.</p>
            <p>I proceed to ſuggeſt ſome motives to this duty of <hi>praying for all men,</hi> and particularly for our Enemies, thoſe who are thought leaſt to deſerve it.</p>
            <p>We are to pray for all Men,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Membra ſumus magni corporis, Natura nos cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natos ſecit. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca.</hi>
               </note>1. Becauſe we all partake of the ſame common na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and are Brethren of the ſame Heavenly Father, <hi>who of one blood hath made all the nations of the earth,</hi> and ſtill doth protect and preſerve them by a gracious and careful providence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All Men have an intereſt in the <hi>Redemption</hi> of the common <hi>Saviour</hi> of the World, they are bought with the ſame ineſtimable price, the <hi>precious blood of the Son of God, who would have all men be ſaved and come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> as it follows a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after my Text, and again <hi>verſe</hi> 6. <hi>Who gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a ranſome for all:</hi> So that the Rich and the Poor, the little and the mighty ones of the Earth meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and God is not only the <hi>Creator,</hi> but the <hi>Redeemer</hi> of them all.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All Men ſtand in need of <hi>Prayers,</hi> and are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of receiving benefit by them; and therefore we are not to withhold this charity, eſpecially conſidering,</p>
            <p n="4">4. That hereby we may do a great deal of good at a very cheap rate, at little or no coſt and expence. No Men have Eſtates to relieve all; Some Mens will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them to give Alms; but to few; Others have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing to ſpare for any; But there is no Man
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104261:5"/>ſo poor, but he may expreſs this charity, not only to ſome, but to all men.<note place="margin">Simplicius.</note> 
               <hi>Paupertas impenſae impedimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, voluntatis non item.</hi> Poverty indeed doth diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our <hi>Beneficence,</hi> the bounty of the <hi>hand;</hi> but not our <hi>Benevolence,</hi> the bounty of the <hi>heart,</hi> our good will and our good wiſhes. By them the Poor may relieve the Rich; the mean and low ones, the high and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Earth; by them we may do good to thoſe whoſe faces we never ſaw, and whoſe complaints we never heard; Our <hi>Prayers</hi> are under no confinement, they can viſit the diſtreſſed afar off, as well as thoſe that are near, and by them our charity may embrace all the World. Who would not be a Benefactor when ſo little goes to make him one? Who would not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to oblige all mankind when he may do it ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily?</p>
            <p>I know ſome will be apt to complain, that praying for enemies, for the ſpightful and cruel, for ſuch whoſe malice is levelled againſt our Perſons and our Religion, is <hi>a hard ſaying:</hi> but to facilitate this duty, let ſuch conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That herein we imitate, and are made like to our Heavenly Father, in whom alone goodneſs is perfect.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
               </note>
               <q rend="inline">How is he every day blaſphemed and diſhonoured? provoked ſometimes by Believers, as well as Infidels, both in word and deed? What doth he do hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Doth he preſently extinguiſh the light of the Sun, and arreſt the Moon in its courſe, daſh the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens in pieces, and tear up the foundations of the Earth? Doth he dry up the Sea, and ſtop the running of the Springs? Doth he mix and confound the Air and the other Elements? None of all this; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe he cauſeth his Sun to ariſe; he gives rain and fruitful ſeaſons; he produceth nouriſhment out
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104261:6"/>of the Earth, for blaſphemers, ungrateful wicked Men, and perſecutors, and that not for one two or three days, but throughout the whole courſe of their lives; Let us go and do likewiſe ſo far as humane frailty will permit. We cannot make the Sun ariſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the World, but we may by our <hi>Prayers</hi> derive ſomewhat of Gods infinite goodneſs upon it; we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give rain, but we may forbear pouring out curſes; we cannot give food perhaps <hi>to our enemy when he hungers,</hi> yet we may forbear revenge and injury.</q> If we can do him no other real good, ſtill we may pray for him, and by this, we ſhall in ſome degree, reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our Father which is in Heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We hereby conform to the pattern, as well as to the precepts of our bleſſed Lord and Maſter, who was not provoked to any impatience under his ſufferings by the higheſt affronts and indignities that were put upon him, or to any expreſſion of ill will towards thoſe that inflicted them; <hi>He was led as a lamb to the ſlaughter, and as a ſheep before her ſhearers is dumb, ſo opened he not his mouth,</hi> more than to pray for thoſe that cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him, <hi>Father forgive them for they know not what they do.</hi> This humility, and condeſcenſion of kindneſs was the height of his Glory: and truly it is the ſingular excellency and perfection of his Religion, as hath been already intimated, that it inſtructs us to imitate this charity of his. For your further encouragement I might ſet before you the examples not only of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and patience, but of the admirable charity of many holy Martyrs in ſeveral ages of the Church. But I ſhall at this time only point you to the great Martyr of this day, and it is very obſervable what high degrees of this truly Chriſtian Charity warmed his Royal heart, how full he was of compaſſion towards his moſt cruel,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104261:6"/>and deadly enemies, not only praying for them upon the ſcaffold, but in his Cloſet devotions: <hi>Thou who madeſt thy Son a Saviour to many that Crucified him, O let the voice of his blood be heard for my murtherers, louder than the cry of mine againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all this ſome perhaps may ignorantly alledge that of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 17.9. for a diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in this caſe, if not for a contrary practice, <hi>I pray for them, I pray not for the world, but for them which thou haſt given me.</hi> But we are not by theſe words to underſtand that our Saviour did wholly leave wicked men out of his prayers, but he preferred his Apoſtles and faithful ſervants before them, theſe were neareſt his heart, and peculiarly dear to him: and as there are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in Gods kindneſs, ſo may and ought there to be in our prayers; whileſt we pray for all men, we are to pray more eſpecially for ſome.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For our kindred, near relations and intimate friends. With what ardency, and tranſports of zeal <hi>Moſes</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> prayed for ſuch, we read <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.31, 32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Church of God, for the whole congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſtian people. The City of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was heretofore honoured above all the Cities of the world, by Gods placing his name there, and by that ſolemn worſhip, which was there performed to him, when the Tribes came up thither thrice a year, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon which account it was a Type of the true Church, and the whole company of Gods faithful people are called,<note place="margin">Zach. 12.1 Heb. 12.22.</note> 
               <hi>the houſe of Jacob, and the inhabitants of Jeruſalem. The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Jeruſalem.</hi> And therefore they were to pray for the Church under this title, <hi>Pray for the peace of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Pſalm</hi> 122.6, 7. <hi>Peace be within thy walls, and proſperity within thy Palaces, &amp;c.</hi> The Lord
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104261:7"/>would not <hi>have them hold their peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 62.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>for Jeruſalems ſake, nor give him any reſt till he made it a praiſe in the earth.</hi> And it was a moſt fervent and pathetical <hi>Prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 9.16.</note> that of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s, <hi>O Lord, according to all thy righteouſneſs, let thine anger and fury be turned away from thy City Jeruſalem thy holy Mountain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe for the ſins and the iniquity of our Fathers, Jeruſalem and thy people are become a reproach to all that are about us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And doubtleſs we under the Goſpel, have all reaſon to own the ſame or greater obligations, to pray for the Peace and proſperity of the Church of God; and if we are not wholly devoid of the ſpirit of Chriſtianity, we ſhall expreſs a ſympathy with our fellow members, <hi>rejoycing with thoſe that rejoyce, and weeping with thoſe that weep,</hi> praying moſt affectionately for thoſe of the ſame holy communion with our ſelves, that God would be pleaſed to confirm them in his truth, keep them ſound in the faith, ſuccour them by his grace, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them by his power,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.17, 18, 19. Epeſ. 1.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>deliver them from every evil work, and preſerve them to his heavenly Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this, among others, we have the example of our Apoſtle <hi>praying</hi> for the Churches,<note place="margin">Col. 4.3. 1 Theſ. 5.25.</note> as well as deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>prayers</hi> for himſelf upon all occaſions, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly when he foreſaw that he ſhould meet with, enemies in <hi>Judea, Rom.</hi> 15.30, 31. This is left upon record, as an honourable teſtimony of <hi>Epaphras</hi> his <hi>zeal</hi> for the Church and people of God, <hi>That he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured fervently for them in prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 4. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>that they might ſtand perfect and compleat in all the will of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But it may be objected againſt this part of our diſcourſe, that there is no ſuch need of praying for the Church, becauſe God hath undertaken to ſecure it, promiſing,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>That the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104261:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, Chriſts Church ſhall never totally fail, but no particular Churches ever had a Patent of perpetual preſervation: The decays and ruins of the Eaſtern Churches are a deplorable inſtance of the contrary, and what hath been done to one Church, may certainly be done to another; what hath been done in <hi>Aſia,</hi> may be done in <hi>Europe.</hi> Nor is that Church exempt which calleth her ſelf the <hi>Mother and Queen</hi> of the reſt; but as ſhe is fallen already in a ſad degree from her <hi>firſt love,</hi> from her <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>purity,</hi> ſo may ſhe ſoon be caſt down from her <hi>pomp</hi> and <hi>glory.</hi> And indeed when we conſider her Apoſtaſie from the Primitive Faith, in many particulars, we underſtand what great need there was, of that early caution of the Apoſtle, <hi>Be not high minded, but fear.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.20.</note> But to ſay no more of that now. All Gods promiſes of not fayling and forſaking his people are made with this reſerve, that they do not wilfuly depart from him. As the Prophet ſaid unto <hi>Aſa, The Lord is with you, while you are with him, and if ye ſeek him, he will be found of you;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 15.20.</note> 
               <hi>but if you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him, he will forſake you.</hi> In which reſpect, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out naming any others at preſent, we ſee there is great reaſon that in our prayers and ſupplications for all men we intercede eſpecially for the Church of God, in ſome ſuch words as thoſe of the Prophet, <hi>Spare thy people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joel 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord, and give not thine heritage to reproach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt pray more eſpecially for that part of the Church of God among our ſelves, becauſe a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and a civil added to the Chriſtian relation, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens our obligation to this duty.<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.7.</note> 
               <hi>For my brethren and companions ſake I will now ſay Peace be within thee.</hi> We that are united in the ſame <hi>civil,</hi> as well as <hi>religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> intereſts, muſt needs ſuffer, or proſper together, and therefore ought to unite in mutual interceſſions, to pray
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104261:8"/>moſt affectionately, for one another and the whole body of the kingdom,<note place="margin">Jere. 14.9. Zach. 2.5. Pſal. 147.3.</note> 
               <hi>That the God by whoſe name we are called would not leave us, but be a wall of fire round about us, and the glory in the midſt of us, that he would ſtrengthen the bars of Sions gates, and bleſs all her children within her;</hi> That he would protect his ordinances, maintain his truths among us, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his gracious preſence with us; that he would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the beauty and ſtability of religious government, that errours and hereſies may not infeſt the <hi>Church,</hi> nor injuſtice, treachery, rebellion, diſorder the <hi>State;</hi> but that the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and the <hi>Tribunals,</hi> religion and policy may mutally ſupport and adorn each other; That our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> may be a City compacted and at union within it ſelf, that we may not by any trifling or peeviſh differences among our ſelves open a breach for the common enemy to enter in at, but that we <hi>may ſtand faſt in one-ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note> 
               <hi>and with one mind, ſtriving together for the faith of the Goſpel,</hi> that we may <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend earneſtly for the faith once delivered to the Saints;</hi> that by all honeſt and orderly endeavours we may joyn together to defend and promote the religion of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, the religion of the firſt and pureſt ages, the religion which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſo groſly corrupted, the religion which the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with others, hath ſo happily reformed, the religion which the blood of ſo many Martyrs in the days of our Grandfathers bore witneſs to, the preſent eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed religion of our Country, known to the world by a name which I hope we ſhall never be afraid or aſhamed to own; <hi>The Proteſtant Religion.</hi> For the flouriſhing of this religion, for unity and love among all its profeſſors we ought earneſtly and importunately to pray; Eſpecially at this time, this difficult and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104261:8"/>time, now when thoſe who have ſo long envied our Churches proſperity, are ſo deeply engaged to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate and deſtroy it; ſeeing their diſſembled enmity can no longer conceal it ſelf, but breaks out in rage and violence, ſeeing their malice is already blooded, the courage of their cruelty heightned by ſucceſs, and every day ready to fly in the face of all that ſhall oppoſe them. In this time of our fear and diſtreſs, every man ought to ſtand upon his guard, and if we are allowed no other weapons of defence, or oppoſition, yet not to fail <hi>to lift up holy hands in prayer to cry mightily unto God,</hi> to implore his help when all other fails. Now the Clouds follow after the rain, and new Storms gather every day, and Mens hearts generally <hi>fail them for fear, and for looking after thoſe things which are coming on the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It concerns us I ſay now if ever to pray like Men at Sea, like men in a Tempeſt (to whom a little Religion will ſupply a great devotion) That God would be pleaſed to keep the Ark of his Church ſtill above water, ſupport a ſinking State, calm all our fears, and comfort our hearts with a bleſſed proſpect of peace and ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. That he may do ſo, I ſay again it concerns us to pray with the poor diſtreſſed Mariners in <hi>Jonah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jonah 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>We beſeech thee O Lord, we beſeech thee, let us not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh;</hi> yea it concerns us to awake our ſecure Neighbours and Friends, that either are not apprehenſive of their danger or mindful of their remedy, as the Ship-maſter did <hi>Jonah</hi> in the midſt of that dreadful ſtorm, <hi>What meaneſt thou O ſleeper, ariſe and call upon thy God, if ſo be that God will think upon us that we periſh not.</hi> Times of fear and trouble are, or ſhould be times of prayer and paſſionate importunity,<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.16.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, in trouble have they viſited thee, they have poured out a prayer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104261:9"/>when thy chaſtning was upon them. In their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they will ſeek me early.</hi> Thoſe are very graceleſs wretches indeed who will not go to God for help, when they need it ſo much; thoſe that do not pray hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily at ſuch a time, it is to be feared that at other times they pray not at all. But to encourage our ſelves in this duty let us conſider, how acceptable our Prayers are unto God at ſuch times, and how beneficial to our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How acceptable they are to God, as appears by that in the Pſalms,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15. James 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>Call upon me in the day of trouble, I will deliver thee:</hi> by St. <hi>James</hi>'s preſcription, <hi>Is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny afflicted? let him pray.</hi> Gods power and providence is more acknowledged, and his goodneſs more eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a <hi>Deliverance</hi> than in a <hi>Preſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider how advantageous it will be to our ſelves; Our ſtrength and help lieth not in our own counſels, in our Purſes, our Policies, our Armies at Land, or our Fleet at Sea;<note place="margin">Prov. 21.31.</note> but the <hi>name of the Lord is</hi> the only <hi>ſtrong tower</hi> for Perſons or States to fly unto; It <hi>is not in the battle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerem. 9.23.</note> 
               <hi>the horſe or rider, but ſafety comes from God.</hi> It is not in the State, <hi>the wiſe man, nor the rich man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>nor the mighty man, but judgment and kindneſs come from God.</hi> When <hi>Iſrael</hi> had deſtroyed her ſelf, in God alone was her help, and he promiſeth to be her King.<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.1.</note> 
               <hi>God is a preſent help in trouble,</hi> our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity is the opportunity of the Divine Mercy. This <hi>David</hi> found,<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.6.</note> 
               <hi>in my diſtreſs did I call upon the Lord and cried unto my God: and he heard my voice out of his Temple.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerem. 26.19.</note> This <hi>Hezehiah</hi> found, <hi>did he not fear, and beſought the Lord, and the Lord repented him of the evil which he had pronounced againſt them.</hi> This <hi>Nehemiah, Daniel, Jonah,</hi> and many others have found, <hi>they cryed unto the Lord in their troubles, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104261:9"/>he delivered them out of their diſtreſſes.</hi> Neither is there any reaſon at all, that we ſhould doubt of the like good effect, if we pray to the ſame God, in the ſame condition, and with the ſame affections, as they did. I have not time to ſhew you particularly, and at large, how your Prayers muſt be qualified, if you expect they ſhould be ſucceſsful, I ſhall only mind you, <hi>That God heareth not ſinners, that if you regard iniquity in your hearts,</hi> live in the allowance of any Sin, God will not hear you for your ſelves, much leſs for others. In ſuch a caſe we only preſume upon God's favour, but do indeed provoke his diſpleaſure, while we continue impenitent and unreformed: we affront his Majeſty by our unhallowed ſacrifices,<note place="margin">Prov. 15.8.</note> 
               <hi>The prayer of the wicked is an abomination to him;</hi> to ſuch he ſaith, <hi>when ye ſpread forth your hands I will hide mine eyes from you, yea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>when ye make many prayers I will not hear: your hands are full of blood.</hi> That our Prayers therefore may be effectual, we muſt ſee that our repentance be ſincere, humbly acknowledging <hi>our wickedneſs and the iniquity of our Fathers,</hi> our unthankfulneſs for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, for our peace and plenty, our civil and religious priviledges, our diſcontents, diſſatisfactions, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience under the beſt Governours, The moſt exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable crime, the barbarous murder which hath ſtained the memory of this day, the guilt and blemiſh whereof we ought to endeavour to waſh off, if poſſible, with the tears of godly ſorrow. In vain may we hope to ſee better days unleſs we can heartily lament <hi>the ſin of this,</hi> the ſins of all our days paſt, and reform our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent miſcarriages, thoſe abominable vices which are inconſiſtent with any Religion, and therefore the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er reproach to ours, which not only pretends more to holineſs, but gives the ſtricteſt rules of life, not ſelling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104261:10"/>at any rate, not granting Abſolutions to any who do not as well forſake as confeſs their-ſins, nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing any Penances ſhort of the mortification of their Luſts.</p>
            <p>We cannot reaſonably expect any good return of our Prayers, unleſs they be attended with hearty reſolutions of amendment of life; It is not Faſting and Prayer, Alms and Prayer, Tears and Prayer, but Prayer and Holineſs, Prayer and a general Reformation that will avail. Repentance is the beſt argument to move God to Mercy, and a holy life is a continual interceſſion. <hi>Beloved, if our hearts condemn us not, then have we confidence toward God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>and whatſoever we ask, we receive of him, becauſe we keep his commandments, and do thoſe things that are pleaſing in his ſight.</hi> It is good counſel for us, to be ſure, which <hi>Zophar</hi> gave <hi>Job. If iniquity be in thy hand, put it far away, and let not wickedneſs dwell in thy tabernacles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 11.14.</note> 
               <hi>For then ſhalt thou lift up thy face without ſpot, thou ſhalt be ſtedfaſt, and ſhalt not fear.</hi> There will be no fear, no danger where there is no guilt. Nothing but our ſins can alienate us from the favour and the protection of the Almighty; nothing elſe can defeat our Prayers, infatuate our counſels, weaken our endeavours, give courage and ſucceſs to our adverſaries. If our Religion have better effects upon us than theirs hath upon them; if it make us more righteous, more ſober, more godly, more charitable, more peaceable, more loyal, than theirs doth them, if it exceed theirs as much in its efficacy, as it doth in its principles, God will then eaſily be intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for us, he will be ſure then <hi>to be on our ſide,</hi> and <hi>we need not fear what man can do unto us.</hi> We need not fear the ſubtilty, or the ſtrength of our Enemies, but we may hope upon good grounds, that the ſame
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104261:10"/>Almighty Saviour, who delivered this Kingdom and Church from that formidable and as it ſeemed invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Armado in 88. That he that blew up the deep de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Powder Plotters, and by a miraculous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery did then preſerve our King, our Princes, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and the whole Parliament, and with them our <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> from a dreadful deſtruction; That he that hath ſo often diſappointed the confidence, defeated the counſels, laid open the moſt ſecret Plots of our Romiſh adverſaries againſt the lives of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Rulers, and the Being of our Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; That he that brought order out of the greateſt confuſion of a Civil War, and a lawleſs Government, he that ſo powerfully and graciouſly reſtored our preſent Sovereign, recovered our <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> from their deſolate ruines, and hath, by a no leſs wonderful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, lately preſerved our King from ſo many devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh conſpiracies againſt his Crown and Life: I ſay we have good reaſon to hope that the God who hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto delivered us, will ſtill do ſo, in our greateſt fears and perplexities; if we turn from our evil ways by repentance, and turn unto him by earneſt, and fervent Prayer. He will not caſt off his people,<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.14.</note> nor forſake his inheritance.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhewed you, that in our general Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for all Men, we are under an eſpecial obligation to pray for the Church and Country whereof we are a part; and I have directed you how to pray, how to ask, ſo that you may obtain: I muſt proceed to ſhew you in the next place, that as you are to pray for the whole body of the Kingdom, ſo more eſpecially for the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Governour</hi> of it, for the King as ſupream, and all Magiſtrates under him, and this my Text exacts of me. <hi>I exhort firſt of all that Supplications, Prayers, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſions,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104261:11"/>and giving of thanks be made for all men for Kings and all that are in authority,</hi> whether they be good or bad; for the good, that God would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to confirm and proſper them in their vertuous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and keep their <hi>hearts ſound in his Statutes;</hi> for the bad, <hi>That he in whoſe hands are the hearts of Kings to turn them whitherſoever he will,</hi> would convert and reform them by a mighty grace, that he would pardon their ſins, that he would ſubdue them to his obedience, over-rule them by his power, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them from acting any thing either to their own, or the publick detriment. The Kings, whom the firſt Chriſtians were to pray thus for, were not only Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, without the Church, but bitter Enemies to it, and bloody perſecutors of it, for Idolatry, Cruelty, and Tyranny, <hi>humani generis portenta,</hi> the Monſters, the Prodigies of their time, and kind; yet theſe wicked Kings and Emperours muſt be prayed for, much more Chriſtian Princes, the <hi>nurſing Fathers of the Church;</hi> much more our own King in whoſe life and welfare we are ſo nearly concerned. Let us pray heartily for him, what we pray every day for him, <hi>that he may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way incline to Gods will, and walk in his way;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching Him alſo, by whom Kings reign, to eſtabliſh his Throne, defend his perſon, direct his Counſels, and ſhew him the things that belong to his own peace, and the peace and ſecurity of his people. I ſhall give you ſome reaſons and motives to enforce this duty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such as are more general, to move us to pray for all Kings at all times.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such as more particularly ſhould ſtir us up to pray for our own King at this time.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One great motive to pray for Kings and all in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104261:11"/>Authority, is the motive in my Text, <hi>viz. That we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.</hi> The whole Kingdom ſhare in the well-doing and proſperity, and alſo in the miſcarriages and misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, of a Prince; He is the light of his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if he be quenched, nay if he be but clouded, or eclipſed, what darkneſs and confuſion, what diſcomfort and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour preſently overwhelms the whole State! As the Sun, and Stars, are ordained in nature to give vigour and life to Trees, Plants and other ſublunary crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; ſo is the face and countenance of Authority ſanctified by God for the cheriſhing and quickning, for the ſtrengthing and refreſhing, all the ſeeds of piety and religion, that are by our miniſtry ſown in the hearts of men. Their laws, their protection and their example have an influence upon <hi>godlineſs</hi> as well as <hi>honeſty;</hi> The power and Juriſdiction of Chriſtian Princes reaching the <hi>Church</hi> as well as the <hi>State.</hi> And however <hi>Mariana</hi> and other Jeſuites have determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>ut nihil Princeps de religione ſtatuat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mariana cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> excluding Kings from all Eccleſiaſtical government, and making St. <hi>Peters</hi> pretended ſucceſſour, the Pope, ſole Monarch here; yet if the high Prieſt had arrogated ſo much in <hi>Davids</hi> time, He himſelf had not ordered the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and attendance of the Levites as we read he did 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.22, 23. nor in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> time,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 30.</note> who him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf appointed the ſervices of the Prieſts and Levites, and gave ſpecial order by Royal Edict, for the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the great Paſſover, and that too at an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual time. Yea it might eaſily be ſhewed that the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns among all people, not only <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but <hi>Heathens,</hi> have both claimed and exerciſed power over religious perſons, and in religious cauſes as well as others.<note place="margin">Ariſt. Polit. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> The great Philoſopher tells us that the firſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104261:12"/>and principal thing in a Commonwealth is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a care of religion; and in the Scriptures we find not only the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Moſes, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuah, David, Solomon, Aſa, Jehoſapaht, Hezekiah, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, &amp;c.</hi> but the <hi>King of Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Darius</hi> the <hi>Perſian,</hi> publiſhing their Edicts to and fro about the worſhip of their falſe Gods, and of the true God alſo. Neither did the Emperours by ſubmitting to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſuffer any diminution in this part of their Royalty; witneſs <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who honoured Biſhops very high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yet he reſerved to himſelf the power of purging the Church from Idolatry, and eſtabliſhing the worſhip of God,<note place="margin">Enſeb. l. <hi>2.</hi> de vit. Conſtant. c. <hi>1.</hi> Theod. l. <hi>5.20.</hi>
               </note> by his own Imperial Edicts. Witneſs <hi>Jovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> who by their own immediate Acts, reſtored and reformed the pure religion, which <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Valens</hi> had ſo much corrupted, and deſtroyed: Witneſs <hi>Juſtinian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Novel. Conſtit. <hi>131.</hi>
               </note> who eſtabliſhed the Code of the Univerſal Church, conſiſting of the Canons of the four firſt General, and five ancient Provincial Councils, and commanded them to be kept as Laws. I cannot ſtay here to give more inſtances of this nature, ſeeing what hath been ſaid already doth ſufficiently ſhew that Kings and Magiſtrates have a great influence upon the Church, upon our living <hi>godlily,</hi> and therefore are to be pray'd for as ſuch who may and do contribute very much either to the deſtruction, or to the defence of the Faith, <hi>the true Religion.</hi> I need not tell you what a neceſſary dependance all the civil intereſts of a Nation have upon their <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Governour;</hi> nor have I time to ſhew you what glory the honour of a Prince reflects upon his people, what protection and ſecurity they have in his power, his Wiſdom, his vigilance and his goodneſs; I can only tell you, that his good is a common good, and therefore to be prayed for as well for our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104261:12"/>own ſake as his, <hi>that we may lead quiet and peaceable lives in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi> That is the firſt motive to pray for Kings, becauſe the general ſafety, peace, proſperity, and piety of a Nation depends ſo much upon them. A further encouragement to this duty,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In a ſecond place may be this, <hi>viz.</hi> That the prayers and piety of <hi>Subjects</hi> do very much contribute to the procuring and preſerving of good <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates.</hi> As for the iniquity and irreligion of a people God many times juſtly deprives them of a good Prince by ſuffering him to fall into ſin and miſchief, which was the caſe of the incomparable <hi>Joſiah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 23.25.</note> So by religion and righteouſneſs is a Nation exalted, and a Throne eſtabliſhed. If <hi>the wicked be taken from before the King, his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 25.5.</note> If the prayers of ſingle perſons are ſo prevalent for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their friends, what great things may we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from the united devotions of many good men in behalf of a perſon whoſe good redounds to many, and whoſe happineſs is a publick benefit? As you have heard.</p>
            <p>If prayer in ſuch a caſe do not move God, to convert a King from all ſin, and make him do all the good which is in his power; yet we may hope it will, at leaſtwiſe, obtain that reſtraining grace for him which will keep him from being worſe, and hinder him from doing that evil to himſelf or the publick which before he was inclined to.</p>
            <p>We are apt to impute the ill management of things and the evils that enſue thereupon, to the weakneſs or wickedneſs of <hi>Kings,</hi> which perhaps may more juſtly be charged upon the ſins, the profaneneſs and indevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>ſubject,</hi> which very often provokes God to withdraw his guidance and direction, his grace and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104261:13"/>from Princes, giving them up to be ſwayed by ill counſel, to be overpowered by temptation, to be drawn by their own luſts and paſſions to commit ſuch folly and wickedneſs, as becomes a plague, and a ſcourge, to a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 106.32.</note>For the <hi>peoples ſake it went ill with Moſes when he ſpake unadviſedly with his lips. Davids</hi> ſin in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering the people was but a judgment executed on them for their own wickedneſs,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.1.</note> 
               <hi>The anger of the Lord was kindled againſt Iſrael,</hi> (for their ſins no doubt) <hi>and he moved David againſt them to ſay, Go number Iſrael and Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To inſtance in the caſe which was too much our own, It was the peoples ſin, and not his ſurely, which provoked God to deliver up the beſt of Kings into the hands of bloody and deceitful men, to be abuſed and vilified, and afterwards murthered by them; If his good ſubjects had ſpent as much time in ſerious <hi>prayer</hi> for him as thoſe hypocritical Traytours did in their mock <hi>devotions,</hi> we might happily have enjoyed him longer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We are to pray for Kings, becauſe it is the only way the generality can do them ſervice in. Thoſe that cannot help them by their counſel, nor their Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, may by their prayers. This way the charity and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the pooreſt <hi>Cottage</hi> may viſit and relieve the <hi>Court</hi> it ſelf, and the greateſt King may be indebted for his preſervation, his life, his health, the ſucceſs of his affairs, to the <hi>prayers</hi> of his meaneſt Vaſſal.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſtian prudence directs, and Chriſtian charity inclines us to pray moſt for ſuch as moſt need it. Now there are none in many reſpects more indigent and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitous than the greateſt <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Potentates,</hi> none that need <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>interceſſions</hi> more than they,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104261:13"/>and that 1. In reſpect of their great duties, 2. Their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold temptations, 3. Their numerous enemies, ſome in one way, and ſome in another, projecting againſt them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their duties are great and difficult; It is a very hard matter to rule well; a great deal of Wiſdom, a great deal of ſtudy and care, of ſtrength and induſtry is required to make a good Governour. The Maſter or Ruler of a Family, a little Commonwealth, as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> calls it, hath a great deal more to do, a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more ſolicitous thoughts about him, a great many more troubleſome buſineſſes upon his hands, than one of a ſingle, though a dependent, capacity ordinarily hath. The Governour then of a Kingdom which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains not only many Families, but many Corporations and Cities, will find the cares and troubles of proviſion and protection to encreaſe and multiply proportionably.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epicurus,</hi> who would by no means deny the being of a God, yet diſowned his providence, and he did it with ſome ſhew of complement and civility, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it muſt needs be a great interruption of his eaſe and tranquillity to concern himſelf in the government of the World, the ordering, guiding, controuling, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of things ſo much below himſelf. In this indeed he bewraies a very erroneous, a very unworthy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the Supream Ruler of the World, as if the ways and actions of the moſt perfect Being were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the ſame ſtreights, confinements, and fatigues, as ours are; whereas his wiſdom knows all things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as the labour of diſcourſe, and his power can do all things without Stratagem, or contrivance. But the Gods of the Earth, 'tis true, <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,</hi> who in many things not only repreſent, but reſemble the God of Heaven, in this are very unlike
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104261:14"/>him. They do not attain their Wiſdom without diligent ſearch, experience and obſervation, nor employ either it or their power without much toil and diſturbance. And how great ſoever the wiſdom and power, the skill and activity of ſome <hi>Kings</hi> may be to facilitate and lighten the duties and burthen of their Empire, we know to whoſe bleſſing they are indebted both for the one and the other,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 22.40.</note> even to that God who gave <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> an underſtanding heart to judge his people, and girded <hi>David</hi> with ſtrength to battle, to ſubdue thoſe under him, who roſe up againſt him.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing theſe great bleſſings of Heaven are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and continued to Kings ordinarily by Prayer; therefore, in this reſpect, they need our prayers more than any others do. They do ſo alſo,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect of their temptations; their infirmities being the ſame with other Mens; their checks and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints leſs powerful, their miſcarriages of a publick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence: The Devil the great enemy of all good will ply all his advantages againſt them; the World lays all her baits before them, ſhews them all her glory at once, ſhe will not let them want any ſupplies for their luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, any inſtruments for oppreſſion and cruelty, any furniture for Pride and Vanity, nor any flatterers to colour and extenuate their Vices, and ſhew them only the fair ſide of themſelves. Seeing then they are eaſily betrayed into ſin, they muſt needs want great ſupplies and ſuccours of the Divine Grace, to repel their temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to ſecure their innocency, or to pardon their errours and exorbitances, and conſequently many prayers to obtain this Grace, to help them in their need.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are ſurrounded with many enemies, and expoſed to many dangers: The height of their glory
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104261:14"/>raiſeth as much envy as admiration, and makes them more obnoxious to the fury and violence of every ſtorm: How many ambitious and aſpiring minds ſeek to greaten themſelves by their diminution? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſcontented ſpirits, <hi>Sons of Belial,</hi> impatient of the Yoke, are trying all ways to throw off their rule, and if they cannot advance themſelves, to bring them down and lay all level? How many deſperate Fortunes hope to repair themſelves by a Kingdoms downfall?</p>
            <p>We our ſelves have ſeen all this ſadly exemplified, and we can make no defenſe, for the future, equal to the danger, without engaging his help by our prayers, <hi>who giveth ſalvation unto Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 144.10</note> 
               <hi>and ſheweth mercy to his anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. We are obliged to be more inſtant and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in our prayers for Kings, becauſe this is the moſt lawful, and righteous way of remedying what is amiſs in them, and of redreſſing our grievances; if we ſuffer by them, we are not allowed to lift up our hand againſt them though it be in the maintenance of our own right. Gods guard ſecures them, more than their own: <hi>Touch not mine anointed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 16.22.</note> Though <hi>David</hi> himſelf had a fair Title to the Crown, yet his heart ſmote him but for cutting off the skirt of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment, and we know afterwards he cauſed the poor <hi>Amalekite</hi> to be ſmitten to death for having a hand in his blood, though he could not ſo properly be ſaid to <hi>kill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.</note> as to <hi>diſpatch</hi> him, or in our ordinary way of ſpeaking to put him out of his pain, which in ſome caſes would rather have been interpreted a kindneſs, than a cruelty; but this he did, no doubt to ſhew how ſacred and inviolate the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and lives of Soveraign Princes ought to be. Nay we are not allowed ſo much as to lift up our tongues
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104261:15"/>againſt them in any murmurous complaints. <hi>Where the word of a King is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>there is power, and who ſhall ſay to him what doſt thou?</hi> It is not only intolerable inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but impiety in ſome caſes to tell them of their faults.<note place="margin">Job 34.18.</note> 
               <hi>Is it fit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Elihu, to ſay to a King thou art wicked, and to Princes ye are ungodly?</hi> And as we muſt not ſpeak evil to them, ſo neither muſt we ſpeak it of them behind their backs. We muſt not <hi>reproach the footſteps of Gods anointed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 89.51. Exod. 22.28.</note> nor ſpeak <hi>evil of the ruler of our people.</hi> Nay the prohibition reacheth further ſtill, and doth not only reſtrain us from expreſſing our diſlikes of them and their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but from conceiving if poſſible, at leaſt wiſe from harbouring or cheriſhing any ill opinion of them in our own breaſts.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are accountable to God and to none but him for their miſdemeanours; thoſe who arraign them at any other Bar invade the Divine Authority and do encroach upon <hi>Gods</hi> Prerogative as well as the Kings, by a bold and daring impiety: But it concerns us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more to have recourſe to God, to ſeek relief from him by prayer, humbly beſeeching him to give the King his judgments, to guide and direct him in all his ways,<note place="margin">Iſa. 60.17.</note> 
               <hi>to make his Officers peace and his exactours righteouſneſs;</hi> and this we muſt pray too with ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Gods will, and patiently waiting for his help, rejoycing the mean while in the teſtimony of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that we have uſed no indirect means to help our ſelves.</p>
            <p>I have propounded theſe arguments, in ſtead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, to ſhew the reaſonableneſs of this Chriſtian duty of <hi>praying for Kings and all that are in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi> I ſhall now only add this to what hath hitherto
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104261:15"/>been ſpoken in a more general way, <hi>viz.</hi> That our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent circumſtances are ſuch as do furniſh ſome peculiar motives to this duty of praying for our own <hi>King:</hi> As firſt of all,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The great danger that he is in.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The great need we have at this time of his fatherly care and prudent conduct.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We cannot but apprehend him to be in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; becauſe thoſe pernicious deſigns, againſt his <hi>regal perſon and government,</hi> ſeem yet to be but in part diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; becauſe his enemies are ſuch as pretend they have Right and Religion on their ſide, A power to diſpoſe of the Crowns and Lives of Princes, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Subjects from all Oaths of Allegiance, to make <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Treaſon</hi> not only <hi>Lawful,</hi> but <hi>Merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious:</hi> We muſt needs, I ſay, have very ſad and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous apprehenſions of the Kings danger, when we conſider that he is encompaſſed with ſuch Malignant enemies, whoſe <hi>Craft</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> envenoms their <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty,</hi> whoſe very <hi>Religion</hi> is more formidable than Pagan <hi>impiety,</hi> and their Church in the worſt ſenſe <hi>terrible as an army with Banners.</hi> It concerns us therefore moſt heartily to commend him to his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and gracious protection,<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.50. Pſal. 33.10.</note> 
               <hi>who giveth great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances to his Kings, who diſappointeth the devices of the crafty, ſo that their hands cannot perform their enterprize; whoſe eyes are upon the ways of man and he ſeeth all his goings;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 34.21. Pſal. 132.2.</note> 
               <hi>before whom Hell is naked and deſtruction hath no covering: humbly beſeeching him to bring to light the hidden works of darkneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 10.2.</note> 
               <hi>and to take the wicked in the devices that they have imagined; to cloath all his enemies with ſhame,</hi> and to grant <hi>that upon his own head his Crown may long remain, and flouriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:104261:16"/>
            <p n="2">2. We have a great deal of reaſon to pray for our King at this time; becauſe we never ſtood in more need of a wiſe and Religious Prince, <hi>to feed us accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the integrity of his heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.72.</note> 
               <hi>and to guide us by the skilfulneſs of his hands, to ſearch out a matter;</hi> to dive into the depth of our enemies treachery, to ſee through their pretences, and to fruſtrate the counſels of wicked and malicious Men; to diſtinguiſh between his truly Loyal, Honeſt, peaceable Subjects, and thoſe who only flatter with their lips whilſt War and Malice is in their Hearts; to weigh counſels, and actions, and to proceed in ſuch methods of Policy, as are moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſecure the great intereſts of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> The Characters, which in Scripture are given of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> ſhew us what great bleſſings they are to a Nation in times of fear and perplexity, of diſtreſs and calamity. They are called <hi>the ſhields of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 47.9. Ezek. 31.17. Judges 20.2. Iſa. 19.13. Iſa. 44.28. 2 Sam. 14.15. Job 29.15.</note> 
               <hi>the arms of a people</hi> to bear them up, and lead them. <hi>The corners of a State, Paſtors, Angels, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> All which ſpeak them our <hi>Guides,</hi> our <hi>Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> our <hi>Strength,</hi> and <hi>Safety,</hi> as well as our <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Glory:</hi> Wherefore in theſe dangerous and threatning times, now ſo many have <hi>openly declared their ill will to this our Sion;</hi> ſo many <hi>Tobiahs</hi> and <hi>Sanballats</hi> malign our Peace and Proſperity; ſo many <hi>Zeha's</hi> and <hi>Zalmunna's</hi> are ready to take to themſelves the houſes of God in poſſeſſion, we cannot but in ſome meaſure be ſenſible of the great bleſſing of a Proteſtant King, of one who tenders our <hi>Religious,</hi> no leſs than our <hi>Civil</hi> intereſts, and hath hitherto been <hi>a nurſing Father,</hi> as well to the <hi>Church,</hi> as to the <hi>State;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently me muſt needs apprehend that we have a great deal of reaſon to pray for the life and welfare of ſuch a King, for Gods gracious Providence over him,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104261:16"/>and for the continuance of his fatherly care over us; that he may be bleſſed with ſuch <hi>Councillors,</hi> and we with ſuch <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> under him, as may always be zealous for the rights of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as may ſtudy to ſecure the <hi>Kings</hi> juſt power and dominion by <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing, encouraging,</hi> and <hi>advancing</hi> that <hi>Holy Chriſtian Faith,</hi> which produceth <hi>Love, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Good-will</hi> among Men; which teacheth us to be <hi>meek</hi> and good natured, to be <hi>gentle</hi> and <hi>kindly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onated</hi> one towards another; to be <hi>ſubject</hi> to <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities</hi> and <hi>Powers,</hi> to <hi>obey Magiſtrates,</hi> and <hi>to be ready</hi> to every good work.</p>
            <p>I need not ſay much of our preſent exigencies, we cannot but perceive them; and I am as unwilling to raiſe <hi>cauſeleſs jealouſies,</hi> as to contribute any thing to a <hi>careleſs</hi> and <hi>irreligious ſecurity.</hi> I only ſuggeſt this, that if Kings have a great influence upon our <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Tranquillity,</hi> the practice of <hi>Honeſty</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> (as you have heard they have) that there is more cauſe than ordinary that we ſhould pray heartily for our King in theſe ſinful and dangerous times, that God of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodneſs and mercy would <hi>ſave both him and us out of the hands of our enemies, that we may ſerve him without fear in holineſs and righteouſneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him all the days of our lives; that glory may dwell in our land, and all nations may call us bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeeing God hath already been pleaſed <hi>to do great things for us whereof we are glad,</hi> we muſt not wholly paſs by that part of my Text which calls for our gratitude, <hi>our giving of thanks,</hi> but offer unto God the <hi>ſacrifice of praiſe,</hi> as well as <hi>of prayer,</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God for the experience we have had of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and patience in ſparing us hitherto, and for thoſe ſignal pledges he hath been pleaſed to give us of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104261:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>inclination towards us, of his <hi>unwillingneſs to caſt off his people and forſake his inheritance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 94.14.</note> which he hath done by diſperſing many of the clouds which have gathered very thick over us, and often threatned us with an imminent deſtruction; by <hi>light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our darkneſs</hi> and ſhining upon us in ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals of mercy, by warning us ſo graciouſly of our danger, by making thoſe Plots viſible and apparent, which were thought too ſubtle to be diſcerned, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving our incredulity with ſo many repeated and convincing evidences, thereby preparing us wither to avoid or to bear the ſtroke; inſomuch, that if we will not, with a careleſs and obſtinate ſtupidity, <hi>put the evil day far from us,</hi> or meet our ruine, we may fairly eſcape it; Whereas God might juſtly have ſurprized us in our ſecurity, and overwhelmed us in a ſuddain and inevitable calamity, <hi>Whoſo is wiſe and will obſerve theſe things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.43.</note> 
               <hi>even they ſhall underſtand the loving kindneſs of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have not time to ſpecify the circumſtances of Gods great goodneſs to us, in diſcovering ſo much of the late horrid Conſpiracy againſt the <hi>Sacred</hi> life of our <hi>Second Charles,</hi> and againſt that Holy Religion which is at once the <hi>Support</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of his Empire. I ſhall only exhort you to magnify the name of our good God, <hi>who is worthy to be praiſed, O give thanks to the Lord, for he is good, for his mercy endureth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael who only doth wondrous things:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 16.34. Pſal. 72.18, 19. Pſal. 106.48.</note> 
               <hi>and bleſſed be his glorious name, for ever; and let the whole earth be filled with his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael from everlaſting to everlaſting, and let all the people ſay Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:104261:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
